you
hi all good evening guys give me a thumbs up if I'm audible and wish
people great let me share my screen do let me know if you can see the screen
share also will get started at 9 or 10 let's say I have eight minutes time okay
so guys who were there in class how's your contest had gone is everyone
attempted it I see one thumbs up it was good and able to clear cook a great
mission it's not good for me I've enough anything specific like any challenges
you faced or did you attempt and practice mode again have doubt on two
questions Kabir okay great we'll discuss them but I've you know what's your
challenge did you attempt and practice mode again so guys whoever have
attempted that's great you know we can pick it up in doubt session
MCQs only and all topics are covered in class yeah hopefully but if few people
okay while selecting MCQs that's fine but you can go back into practice mode
and you can reconfirm Abhinav whether the answers were right or what's the
point of you know giving equation that way so I would highly suggest you to go
back into the practice mode and just see them again whichever you were not able
to attempt it and see if you are able to clear because it will take hardly 20 to
30 minutes or I guess not more than that right so I saw other people a few
questions had more than one answer does anyone feel same okay how many of you
order Kiran says I see one thumbs up okay I actually didn't see the questions
maybe if I have seen I could have comment more on that but but overall
experience was good enough right did you feel those questions were like or the
topics that we have already covered
yeah so Muneshwara says that a session on MCQ test that I have to see I will
check with the team and get back on that Abhinav like because I need timeline and
you know to I'll check on that and I'll let you know if I can pick it up a
session okay yeah okay so and how's your weekend had gone guys so how's
everything going at your workplaces and how's everyone doing so one messing up
topic in my head I shouldn't actually talk about it
marriages say some bit hectic I know so how many of you are following a
project where elections is happening I don't talk more on that but just want to
know how many of you are curious hectic schedule for me to going to office okay
I get that curious on what like how many of you are following up on projects of
election like what's going on in there in today and tomorrow do you feel it
same like what the prediction like BJP is sweeping again everywhere there's too
much things going on anyways that's out of topic thing so anyone going through
interviews guys any experiences you want to share if anyone is trying to
interview at different workplaces because I've seen right no no we have an
option some bit we always have an option because I mean I don't as it in
light I don't want to share my opinions on public platform but we do have an
option always regional specific like when you come to my state we had to we
picked it up so that that's okay anyways like it's it's one perception once
understanding right no worries guys don't want to go into that depth but
there's any any reviews any feedbacks related to anyone appearing any you know
interviews or taking up waiting to complete react up left okay great some
cover that most probably next month we are going to start and nine eighty
percent of thing I'll be completing in next month itself so but one thing guys
please take care of it so that whenever we are completing any topic I've given
you a few links right to where to study from things related to JS try to read
the content from that try to cover all the topics that we were discussing so
that you know we are on page okay okay great so guys can anyone drop in what's
people today I'll drop myself let's see
and
it's summer everywhere right to like you know completely dry in our in my state
this my place the wind is blowing you feel hands getting dried skin is getting
dried here yeah I will be taking up react cover so we'll be getting started
with react next year's projects I'll be covering all of them so hopefully I'll
be delivering the content that up to a standard that you're expecting it okay
okay this I didn't know for the last one minute you get a like red border box
shadow border so guys anyone anyone working on building projects anyone
tried it out new thing or anyone curiosity of like seeing any application
or anything how they might have built something in anything that you see
around any website anything we can discuss over that thing if you feel
something curious about any particular thing let's discuss that thing also okay
so I'll stop this I'm trying hopefully we can see some okay great magnetic
mouse pointer interesting I don't really know that thing open drop maybe
once you share some URL when you deploy maybe we'll explore that but looking
forward to it
okay just a minute place you can drop me a ping some bit then we can maybe
connect because I have to manage my time right so once please check with me
before directly picking me up you can bring me anytime it's just that I had I
will check off from my side and we'll let you because if you have heard it we
just have gone through live offset PayPal and that too many things going at
work at my workplace too so still you know the we are hiring leadership
continuously our new CU is hiring leadership so the things changing very
frequently inside so we are also a bit confused whom to report whom to change
my report my manager got changed twice so we are still in bit of mess I'm not
sure how things are but just bring me up I'll try to find time and connect with
you okay so guys can we get started with today's class we are on time great so
just just trying to you know revise the content what we have covered till now if
you if you remember when we started with oops firstly we have covered
constructor function and we covered this keyword in all the context different
context and once we cover this then we went on to understand you know class
space syntaxes for the constructor function and also classical inheritance
we can say this where you extend a particular class and we we have seen
that and we have also converted a class into a function and you know the
functions into prototypes and I have left with one question to you all like
how do you handle static keyword inside a class convert into the functions in
function use case like constructor function use because did anyone able to
explore this one they didn't even get any chance to explore this one like
declaring whatever static methods are there inside a class let's say you have
a class a or you have a static test we had the syntax we know that if we want
to convert this into this we can talk about function a and then how do we
handle this like do you go a dot prototype dot test equal to something
how do you declare it have anyone got chance to explore this part related to
static try to check on this guys if you haven't done it okay no no worries not a
big deal because it's I don't want to say it that way but not that important
okay but try to explore that like how this has been built actually because
those are the features been provided from the constructor function level just
try to explore that now the last topics from the object render programming are
left us like few higher-order functions that we should be knowing it so if you
remember the higher-order functions that were declared you know studied on array
where like filter map you know and reduce similarly we have here the other
higher-order functions like call apply wine and so what is the definition of
higher-order function base how many of you remember what is this HF HF what we
call it as higher-order function
anyone remembers this one okay it's a function which takes in a function or
returns a function from it right yeah right so we have actually generally we
have to declare read three methods this particular functions we have to
understand then other than this single we'll again talk about something called
as pass by value versus pass by reference this thing I think I have
already covered it but I'll give you a glimpse of it again then I'll talk
about like you know shallow copy like versus deep copy how can you make a
shallow copy versus a deep copy so we'll talk on these two things other than
this thing there's a one extra thing that I want to talk about is like this
might I might cover in doubt session but if you're interested you can stay back
and listen it like I'll actually implement this this function library
function call in normal like if someone asked you to implement call how would
you do that so we generally say write a polyfill for call so I'll cover that
part if we want to cover in the class itself we cover or we'll take it up in
a drought session okay guys so is the agenda part here what if what we are
going to cover this is the part today what we are going to cover it okay let's
get started with that then okay let's go back to directly visual studio code
okay I don't have yes code
let me create a new class class 23
and let's do one thing let's create something file callers index.js now so
let's start this focus on this thing let's say I build one object called
student okay a simple object again taking taking that same generic object
like where it has a first name and last name let's say I pick it up a first name
as an Adam and last name as Smith and let's say age of this particular person
is 25 and let's say there's a function called get email which returns instead
of returning it let's say we are trying to console dot log where what we are
trying to console log is let's say simply this dot first name and last name
and now let's say if I execute this way get email what should be my output guys
what should be my output if I execute this way this is straight forward we have
done this multiple times so if I'm calling that function add up Smith
right let's say if I execute this one to show you guys that this is the same
thing that as you expect note index.js I'm getting that Adam Adam Smith that's
working fine but now let's say if I create another object called student
then you have teacher let's say there will be a teacher then he will be having
some name let's say the first name of the teacher could be let's say we call
Rohit let's rename teacher as a Rohit Sharma okay and age could be around 37
again let's say I have his get email function so I'm trying to do a function
call again I'm going to do a console dot log
let's say again I execute this one teacher dot get human so still even now
we are expecting rohy Sharma to be printed right so you agreeing with my
point first like rohy Sharma something would need to go printed the console
but let's see what is our problem statement here okay when all these
issues comes in like do you see any common code here common code like
anything in this or everything is common do you see this get email function get
email function like this function is actually same right right so imagine if
this function is taking thousand lines of code thousand lines of code would
you define it this way that a teacher object will have a get email function
again student object will have a again in thousands of lines of code do you
feel this is the right way of writing logics we need to extract that get email
get email out of this thing now let's say what if I try to extract this get
email outside okay let's I get email function so that I want to reuse it what
I'll do here it's like I'll clear let me copy that and paste that function
completely okay what I did I just created that function and now let's say
if I point this get email let's say I call this as this this way and let's say
I point this thing this way and point this one this way okay how many of you
still agree it's still thing that our output will be still same that we still
should get Adam Smith and Rohit Sharma okay let's see two people agreeing if
anyone there's a disagreeing let me know if everyone is agreeing let's see let's
see this if it is working as expected I see one thumbs down but let's review
this one let's say I execute this one now what just happened this what just
happened did I save this clear it okay now I pulled I pulled this get email
function outside and I have added it here it's still working as expected
right it's still working as expected that I'm point taking that reference but
now just let's let me try to you know link this with one of the file index
start HTML just to see that if it is in browser environment also behaving same
let's say I call it as call apply wine
now let's start me with script SRC
now let me go back into the browser let me paste this and let me open inspect
tool for seeing the console locks now refreshing this one now let's say if I
go back so now do you see this like firstly that I'm having this email
inside this so whenever I'm trying to get the function here I'm actually
getting that whole function and this is being working as expected so this
whatever we think that you know our problem statement would be that is
being solved isn't it like generally so what what was the problem statement that
what if I want to like let's say there's a code now which I pull it outside and I
keep it commonly here then I can reuse it for everything instead of writing
multiple times but what if there wasn't a use case what if there wasn't a use
case let's say I create another two functions let's say const student one
okay again trying to copy the same thing okay now let's say instead of creating a
common function outside I have a function here and let's say I have a
teacher and it's I make it teacher one and that's I don't have this function
so what if like if we can use this function somehow like now if you see
earlier what we have done we have pulled out a function outside and we made it to
work like so we removed the duplication of code following the type type
principle that's all great can we write
yeah okay so I'll come to that I'll come to that I'll come to that Kiran but
let's focus on this like let's take this example second thing now if you see it
here what I just did it is that I created another object called student
one inside that there is a get email function and teacher want to use this
function somehow which is present inside the object can can we do this also
somehow like what if we can call this one like anyone having any ideas so Kiran
says proto now so you are saying that something let's say I say that teacher
one dot prototype okay equal to student one is it this is what you're trying to
suggest Kiran okay is there any other way is there any other way now so first for
let's see like can I can I do it something this way that it's a call
student one dot get email and I can I can pass something the values of this
one let's say if I can pass values of first name and last name of teachers
object you assume okay huh super no ways exactly think of this one that how
we can actually pass the object because if you see when I'm making a student one
dot get email now you know that the this pointer is actually referring to this
Adam Smith I need 25 right that point is clear from our earlier classes but now
here if I want to borrow here function let's say if I want to borrow function
from different object and execute it now when I want to borrow and I want to
change the context where this is referring to is this point clear like I
want to change this referring to inside student one right so is there any way
that you can think of like how we can do that so one of the way what Kiran
suggested is like you can use a prototype and you can leverage that but
that's fine but is there any other way that you can think of now here's where
guys here's in those cases itself where this all these functions comes now what
this problem what these things are solving if I say let's say call bind
apply all are solving same problem in different ways now what problems are
actually solving is that if you want to change the context of this keyword
a particular function is
is referring to then we can use call apply by okay so I hope you got the
stuff what actually we are about going to do is that if you want to change
like what this get email is referring right because if I want to borrow this
function and I want to make this teacher object actually this Rohit Sharma to be
passed inside this then I have to do something leveraging these things okay
now the another thing that I can show you here is that let's say what happens
when I instead of now let's say if you see I have get email object now let's
say if I remove this one okay I remove this one now earlier this was working
fine if I remove it and I call directly get email function do you still think
that the output will be still same like as earlier like wherever when you are
getting Adam Smith and Rohit Sharma if I directly refer to this function so I see
two people are saying still yes so let's see this guys once verifying this now do
you see this that it says that you know get email function is not an object
because firstly we are calling that function on this object object doesn't
have this function you are surely that you cannot call it but how can you
leverage this until unless you don't have a key value pair inside this let's
say whenever you have only key value pair pointing to inside a function only
then you will be able to call right so one of the way of solving this problem
earlier was like wherever code duplications happens and all the
context inside this is referring with this keyword is always trying to pull
out a function and writing a generic function again still appending that
instead of duplicating again still attaching the reference to it one way
the other way around is using this keyword stack call this apply now what
call apply and this does it is that it keeps you ability to change the context
of particular function now let's say how we can change the context of this one
what I'll do is that let's say now if you see I cannot pass here the teacher's
object first so let's say what we can do it is that on student let's say if I go
on the student and get email function on every function you will be able to see
call apply bind will be available let's say okay now every time on every
function that you see in JS you will be able to see call apply bind now what
they are solving if you see here they are solving the same problem that is
what I say in first statement in second statement what are trying to say is that
let me make it as a multi-line comment here so that we are able to refer this
one right away let's say this is the line one and let's say this is line two
okay now so firstly what we are saying is that this all are solving the same
problem but and what problem they are solving if you want to change the
context of this keyword okay in a particular function okay this is
referring to then we can use call bind apply now what I'm doing it is like
let's say student dot get email in the student dot get email function if you
see this is always referring to these two keywords but I want to change such a
way that it refers to Roy Sharma what I'll do is that I should pass the object
first okay if you see the first parameter it takes something is called
as this function now let's say if I pass a teacher teacher one this will still
execute in a same way let me try to you know comment this logic clear this
clear this re-execute this so one thing I'll do it is that I'll comment
everything on the top so that you get complete just of it now so guys are you
able to see this like what just happened firstly is that I call something like
student dot get email we know that when we learned you know in the first class
where we are learning this it should have been referring to Adam Smith but it got
changed to teacher when we used this call function okay how many of you are
able to understand problem statement and solution give me thumbs down if you're
not able to follow up guys I'll write try to show you in the debugging format
this is changing now the function of this call is just doing changing where
to what this is referring to okay okay I'll anyways explain this again let's
say we don't have this function itself let's say we don't let's say we don't
have this function itself let's say if I go to this use case the other example
okay now in when I execute this get email function what what could be the
value of this case simply if I call this function get email function and if I
try to do console log of this what should be expected in non-strict
environment let's say I'm executing in the browser you would be getting a
window object isn't it window object how many of you agree with this point
that you will be getting let's say if I try to console log firstly let's say
console dot log this year okay and I try to call this function first let's say
get email function okay and if I go back into the browser where is the browser
okay now if you see I'm printing that window object that is coming from index
to now what call will solve this now call will say that hey don't refer to
the window refer to the object whichever I'm sending it are you able to relate
with this point guys firstly did you understand that our default function
whenever we execute in non-strict environment we get window object is
there is anyone still who don't understand this point guys get give me
some reaction so that I'm able to follow up okay so now what I'll do it here let's
say if I want to execute this function changing the context of this let's say
now it's printing window object and I'm getting undefined keys right if you see
I'm getting window and undefined undefined because there's nothing like
first name and last name existing inside this now let's say if I do get email
function now as I said you on this function by default you will have all
these methods call blind apply now just taking this and passing the student
object on in it when I do this it will change the context from this referring
to window object to this object so we are changing what this is pointing to
okay let's see if this is working fine if you see here when I changed it the
particular thing which was pointing to window object got changed to the object
that we mentioned and it printed Adam Smith so I able to relate what call is
actually solving so let me show you in pictographical way also which will give
you better idea further so let's say in a function there's a function and you
are trying to use this keyword anywhere and this keyword we know that it can be
either window or an object undefined or empty string or global right these are
the things that we know it but what if any time if they are referring to this
least of least of things at a dynamic way if you want to change this
particular thing whatever it is pointing to then we can say that whatever let's
say this is a function a I can say that a dot call and I can pass the object
that I want once I point object passes object this will be always referring to
this object instead of this one whatever generic thing we learned is this clear
what actually call is doing just changing the context remember that it is
just changing the context where this is pointing to anyone having any doubt now
is anyone having any doubt again I'm rechecking with you guys I hope no one
no let's say when I say that you know all these things are doing still
solving the same problem why we need firstly three methods isn't it now let's
say we add on we keep on add few few more things like okay methods now let's
say if we have this we have the student is and everything let's say I build some
function where also I try to print the other things let's say student also
studies let's say I have something like common cities it's a common items let's
I have an array where say is in Hyderabad and we can say that so city
Montessori and he likes to play cricket okay once we have this yeah so it is
just changing the context but if as you mention it it's it's right thing like it
is changing the object what it is referring to we are changing the object
value whatever this is referring to inside a function using a call okay so
that helps us in order to you know dynamically play around with anything
that we want now let's say that we have the other things guys now what I'll do
is that I'll change this function I'll build another function called get info
and I'll call this function and we try to build the whole let's say information
about this particular student so yesterday's
let's say I have school let's say receive here school city and favorite
sport okay right
no so what I just stated here is that I created a function now just like I try
to break let me try to break this line into two lines firstly there are few
parameters I'm getting from the this object and then I'm trying to get the
other things from the you know functional parameters now if we want to
if we want to let's say if we are clear that okay we can change the context of
this we are calling this function now how can we pass this parameters can we
pass it this way like we call this array and we pass an array and you know this
problem is solved or we have to pass it such a way that I have to give it all
things one by one right because a function might not like oh you know have
everything with related to this keyword like this dot first name it might not be
getting everything from the object there might be some use cases like it
might be getting some constant values right let's say we are grouping a list
of people who are having common first name and last name but I mean first time
and last time are different whereas school cities port are same thing like
they what they likes to play so if you want to build up that category this
reusable function where you whatever object you pass from the student
information they'll have it but school and city information is common so that
we can pass the same values into a function like we know not to maintain in
terms of object let's say we have an array built is this clear guys like what
I'm trying to do here firstly so what I'm trying to say is that how we will be
able to actually you know call this particular things how we can pass on
here using the call method now this the way of writing syntax currently
whatever I have written is completely wrong because if you see here we are
passing this information that's all great that's all great that whatever you
are expecting inside the get email function okay it's not getting well
anymore it's get info let's say I call this get info okay let me clear this and
execute this one if you see still whenever I'm passing it this way and I'm
trying to call it it doesn't execute it as we expected okay because the call
actually the call function whichever is part of this you know we are calling on
get info it's part of its prototype okay the way we can call this one is you need
not to call it directly inside the caller function itself it takes multiple
parameters other than this keyword now let's say if I hover over this do you
see that it talks about this arc array arc you very can pass all the items one
by one now let's say how we can do this let's say if I have this I say that
array dot zero or array dot one or array dot two okay when we do this now let's
say again I clear this part I execute it now do you see this Adam Smith studies
in Hyderabad at City Montessori school and likes to play cricket okay this is
what we are able to print hope the this whatever example I've picked it up I was
just trying to show you that if you have let's say use case of passing extra
parameters into a function which are common and there might be an objects
like teacher a student everything will be different but there might be few
fields which are common across for the common across we have an object which
will I did and added its information but there are some common fields that will
we'll pass it as a constants is this clear guys how this thing works how we
are able to pass extra parameters in case if you want to using call now now
let's say this this is about call guys this is about call that what call does
now let me show you one of the example what bind us can use a spread operator
surely Kiran we can use that I'll talk about that one okay I'll talk about
that one how we can how you can use a spread operator or anything here
firstly if you use this spread operator let's say array do you see this still it
works okay it works with with the spread operator also now what bind us there is
a small difference in call and wine if I still let's take or bind this function
let's say I try to get email fn function and I say that bind bind with student
what I'm trying to do here same as call earlier example whatever we have taken
we we still took that same example like I picked up this object and I picked up
this method I'm changing the what this is pointing to and I'm trying to call
with the student let's say if I save this I'm still try to execute it if you
see I'm able to print Rohit Sharma still right from mind do you see this like
Scholar bind is still doing that same problem solving like they're still
changing the context where this is pointing to now let me okay in browser
I'll show it
let's say I refresh this once we go inside this sorry not bind guys I was
talking about apply give me a second now if you see this once I send apply it is
still changing that same thing and it's trying to print the content yeah if you
see this it's Adam and Adam Smith when is for a do you get this like not
Rosham Rosham is coming from below I'll try to comment that part let me go down
I'll comment this line okay so guys what I did here is that I was talking about
bind I'll talk about in sometime later but now I introduced you new method
like in from the call apply wine I picked it up apply now do you see this
call and apply works in the same way if you see like I've tried to call that
particular apply and I'm past the object of student and I'm trying to print it is
printing that this whatever this is pointing to it got changed then Adam
Smith is something it is printing so still both are doing the same thing then
you might be thinking like a why we need both of these things right what what's a
use case of using call and apply together isn't it so the problem here
what apply is doing is with respect to the extra parameters how we are passing
now let's say if this have let's say if this is having extra 10 parameters okay
if you see this extra parameters we know that these are empty parameters and we
don't really need to you know use them but whereas in call if you see earlier
this spread operator is actually spreading each and every particular part
of an array but how that call takes is that individual elements okay it takes
individual elements but what apply does it takes whole array as an input it
takes array of array of elements whereas this takes individual parameters okay now
let's try to execute this one and verify if you see it still works it still works
right where what do you have what we have got here Adam Smith studies in this
college then we have got still okay let me try to print it using apply
clearing this
now do you see this using call and apply we are still able to print that same
statements but are you able to get the gist of it like one thing is allowing
us to add a complete array and one thing is allowing us to add individual
elements and what apply does it right it picks from the starting index let's
say now if I try to pull it up this way I'll show the difference where things
goes wrong I had it this three elements and let's say as we were doing earlier
we were using a spread operator now let's say if I spread it okay now still
it behaves in same way right so what what's the main thing main goal of this
one is that one thing accepts individual parameter wise like whatever parameters
you mentioned you have to pass them like let's say like as array one array of zero
and one and two whatever syntax this so individual elements you have to pass
whereas in apply it takes array of elements so what what is the use case
like when to use when to when to use call and when to use apply is that
generally whenever you have an like bigger things right where you cannot pass
individually spread operator helps you around actually to use both of things in
the same way but this is a common interview problem interview question
that when to use call when to use apply I'll just explain that point
let's say you have an array which have too many things too many things and one
of the better way is like always you can extract things which is if you are
extracting it then you can use call anyways but before the spread operator
was introduced people used to use apply where they can pass directly object of
this and array instead of individually writing all the parameters like array of
zero array of one array of two is this clear like this is just like how you
want to pass an extra parameters the difference between call and apply is that
how we are dealing with extra parameter
call takes individual values whereas apply takes array of elements so
depending on use case you can use either of them right yeah apply also takes the
whole array and however the function you have written depending on that it will
extract it so both in a way are actually solving the same problem as I say
muneshwaram both are solving the same function same problem statement and they
are actually same thing but it is just like how we are passing the extra
parameters okay let me show this in the internet also for reference that's what
the difference between call and apply if you see the difference is that apply
lets you invoke function with arguments as an array call requires the parameters
to be listed explicitly okay this is the just syntax like this function whatever
function we have apply value for this and array of arcs whatever arguments you
have it takes an array whereas if you go for call whatever object you want to
change to this this then you have to give individual items is this clear guys
what is difference between call and apply pretty straightforward and simple
okay nothing complicated in this now because if you see because why this was
introduced this one actually call and apply if you see here spread operator
for the array was introduced in the year 6 it was not there before but call
apply and bind were present from earlier so now people go and leverage call
directly like where you can use spread operator or can use apply anything that
works for you but there are two methods and why we are discussing both of them
because sometimes in interview they ask it which one to use when and what is the
context of this you can use anything as per your requirement because if you have
an array you can spread it around or else you can write down manually one one
parameter also okay now let's explore this call apply must be present in
prototype right yes Kiran let me show you this one let's say if I do get info
okay dot prototype if you see in this great info prototype here do you see
this inside this prototype or inside the constructor function for the function do
you see here call apply blind the three of them are present or as a core
arguments because they're trying helping you to change the context of this okay
this is how they defined earlier because JS was this is how that Brandon I created
it but in order to you know mix both of things call and apply like we have a
spread operator again both are solving same problem as I earlier told that you
know all the all these three things are solving the same problem now when I say
that bind also solves the same problem how does bind helps us that now let's
say if I want to store this function let's say I say this has a reusable
function now what I can do here is that I can go get info dot bind I can say
that bind with the student and again this bind again takes individual
elements okay now this reusable function if you say earlier when we were
calling this get info dot apply and call that was executing the function for us
but what bind does is bind gives us a it gives us abilities to store this
function and use it whenever you want it because I able to understand this like
it gives us a function now let's say if I try to console dot log reusable and I
also call this reusable once I execute this now let's see the difference if I
go back here so I'm still printing that Adam Smith and everything but if you
see at line number 25 what bind is giving me a bind is giving me to store
function which is having you know the context of this is being changed already
let's see that let's see this in the life what actually happens if I try to
re-execute this one okay we don't need call okay if you see if I try to print
this reusable
let's say let me go here and I'll explore I I'll show it here itself what
is actually happening now if you see it here what happened is inside the
prototype right inside the reusable there is something like call us target
function inside this target function is actually having the function which we
are which we are storing it like get info get info is become the target
function and inside this view whatever this something object we passed it like
which you are changing the context okay then we are also having something called
as array of three inputs if you see this is accepting you know accepting
variables as array is this clear so guys how this bind is working it gives us a
you know storable functions and then you can use it whenever you want it okay so
I hope this context is clear what is call apply wine to you know just
to revise this thing nothing much big thing but just to simply explain this
all of this thing are changing context of this keyword inside function okay
and these methods are part of prototype of a function okay now call takes
two things this checked and individual parameters this is before if I easy
syntax says because spread operator can anyway solve okay whereas apply takes
this object an array of parameters then bind takes this object and individual
parameters and returns and say function now why I said this has a higher order
function is called by and apply because bind actually is returning a function a
function which is returning a function or taking a function in a parameter is
usually called as higher order function that's the reason why I mentioned this
thing okay I hope this call bind didn't get the bind okay let me explain it so
what happened earlier now if you say if you say whenever we are calling this get
email dot call we are passing object and value 1 value 2 so value 3 right this is
executing function immediately similarly you have get email apply which take this
object and you have array of values value 1 value 2 value 3 it still executes immediately
but if you want doesn't want we don't want to execute it but we want to store in some
variable let's say I will use it later then I can say that get email dot bind this again
all these things value 1 value 2 and value 3 so this doesn't get executed instantly I
have to call this whenever I want to use it so these are getting executed instantly this
is like which gives you like willing whenever you want to use it you can use it again Muneshwara
this is you know it takes individual parameters but it is up to you like again you can use yeah
something like callback because it is returning as a function it returns a function which can
be used later so to answer your doubt Muneshwara let's explore this documentation itself okay
if you see this whenever I hover around around this if you see it says this least of arguments
to be passed into the new function okay whenever I say that least of arguments now if I go back
to apply now let's say if I go for apply what it says is that arcs array a set of arguments
to be passed into the function when it says this least of items it is actually asking you to
list on each of the thing it takes this way or else you can always anything as we have discussed
earlier you can spread it around and leverage it okay anything works but I hope this point is
clear like this this is just something is used to change yeah we can change it now if you see
here I pass the student object I'm still using that same object of student I'm changing the
here inside this this should be pointing to window but we are pointing to like student so
it depends on what you are passing in okay the first parameter is object which are trying to
change no context with this is this clear guys how this three things works really basic stuff
we don't need much of time but I just tried to complicate it stretch it around okay I want
to talk about some other concept basic simple concept again let's say memory.js now let's pick
this example guys what like first let's say I have const I say first name I have let's say
muneshwara okay I'll make it let again let's say I have second name some name say bapu so if I
do first name equal to second name and I try to console dot log first name and console dot log
last name second name what is expected guys what is expected to happen once we do this
both a babu will be printing it right so I hope everyone is agreeing guys I'm
receiving only two reactions I hopefully I receive some more reactions okay I see one thumbs down
guys see three people great now let's say that node memory.js yeah it's printing babu babu that's
clear right because now I want to talk about one phenomenon is like no let's say okay I also what
I'll do is that I'll update the second name as let's say instead of so I keep it power then
what is supposed to happen what is supposed to happen this time it will print power power right
let's say let's view this if it is working fine so to how many people this point is clear how
this power power or babu babu is printing is there anyone who is having doubt on this concept
it's clear right now what can we call this can I call this pass by value where from one variable
to the other variable actually I'm passing the value directly can I call this this way that
actually I'm passing a value to the second name I have created new value then to the first name
I'm passing whatever value power is having I'm passing it to it that now let's say I take another
example where I have first name object inside this let me create name again let me pick
something new name let's say I have Kiran and let's say I have let second name object I have
name let me pick now breathe now let's say I try to do something like first name object equal to
second name object now once I do this and I try to console dot log first name object and console
dot log second name object now what is going to print it guys in this example what we are
going to print it if I try to print first name object and second name object both the time it
should be printing love breathe so are you guys aligned with the Muneshwara and Kiran's answer
that every time we'll be printing a love breathe in both the cases guys give me thumbs up or
thumbs down anything works fine just want to know okay great now let's say if we are printing it
this is fine we are printing love within both these cases now what if I go and do something
like once I updated it I go do this one and update the name as let's say no what is supposed
to happen okay Muneshwara says love breathe and Uttam guys how many of you think that
Kiran says Uttam twice so give me thumbs up if you are going with Muneshwara answers give
me thumbs down if you are going with Kiran's answer guys please you know press that button
if you are going with Muneshwara's answer give me thumbs up if not give me thumbs down I see
only five six people reacting this up okay I see many people getting thumbs up so everyone is
aligned with Muneshwara's answer let's see this now so do you see this guys people who gave
eight people including Muneshwara are wrong both the time both the times I'm printing Uttam here
so let's explore this what's actually happening okay let's explore this what's actually happening
behind the scenes what's actually happening now we had something like first name object
inside this we had field called name let's say I call it as first
okay then we had second name object we had name called as second right then what I did
I just updated this first name object equal to second name object then I updated second name
object dot name equal to let's say third I make it as third then we were trying to console log
both things it was printing third and third this was a use case that is happening right now let's
explore this step by step what's actually happening when I declare this things when
I declare this one code is executed think from the call stack point of view when you have the
stack and there is a heap we know that all the memory objects are anything array sort of functions
though those exist in inside the heap area now here we created something like first name object
good enough and then we had something like second name object good enough first name object was
pointing to name first right second name was object was pointing to name second so do you
guys agree with this part till now this is what we have done till this point right then what we
did is we called something like hey can you do this update the first name with the second name
when we did this what actually happened is that this pointer this line got called off then there
is a new line got updated as this one is this clear what happened with this line on this line
so we cancelled this pointer and it updated with the current pointer then I say that second object
name if I'm saying that second object dot name if you see this when I say that second object dot
name now if a second object dot name I'm updating this as a third right let's say I'm updating as a
name third this one and this got already cancelled now both of this are still pointing to this one
and the name is updated as third is this clear why this third is printing third and third to
all the seven people so in terms of object in terms of object whenever we are actually
playing around with those objects right we say that values are passed by reference so
whenever you are passing any object to the other object you are actually passing a reference
pointer you are actually passing this items but you're not passing actual values values are there
in heap values are not greater duplicate okay so is this clear guys what is pass by value versus
pass by reference yeah pass by reference will actually come in terms of objects only because
in the object what happens in terms of like when when it comes to the objects why this has been
created this way is that objects are really huge in size like if you see those are custom
data types it can be sizing like really big thing now if someone try to apply in a skip assigning
this way right those will get duplicated each time they'll get duplicated and the memory will
be used extensively so in order to optimize memory consumption they have created a heap area where
you will put the all the objects and you will point to them so that duplicate objects are not
created for each time so that each will have the same pointing to the same thing is this clear
guys what is pass by value only primitives to pass by value yes only primitive does pass by
value because primitives let's say if you go and back and see that example right let's say I have
name equal to with them when I am doing this line and I'm assigning line this actually happening
called call stack itself it will take name and it will assign it will do it here itself and it
will have the context this value will exist only till the moment that function is executed once
that function is execution is clear that file is cleared this value will be lost this value won't
present but in heap area the objects are still persisting there is something like you know that
cleaner comes who is the person who cleans this one who is the person who cleans this objects guys
from the heap area anyone knows it does anyone know who cleans heap area like first call stack
we know that let's say if you go back and see this example right in the one side once I let's say
this this thing right this part is getting executed this if I remove this file from the browser
context it will be removed but this objects are still present in the heap area because those are
stored in memory but who is supposed to clean these objects or the like because point us once
call stack is executed this point us will go away this point us will go away but in memory when
I appended let's say take this example itself now when we assigned this first name we assigned
first name equal to second name we updated these two pointers pointing to this one but
this memory still exists in heap area right this one no one cleaned it up this is still
consuming memory is this point here is this is still memory is existing this is not this is this
is where memory leak issues comes in and the person who is up actually supposed to do is who
is supposed to clean is called as garbage collector have you heard of this thing garbage collector
earlier so garbage collector come signs he checks what he does he does a simple DFS call you know
DFS right DFS and BFS calls graph calls how they go and check this you know DFS and BFS
you don't know DFS and BFS you might have completed your data structure algorithm right depth first
and breadth first search same same depth first and breadth first now what this there's an algorithm
written inside that it starts with the one node all these objects are nodes in how it is stored
now it starts from one node and it keeps on traveling to the other nodes and it checks
whether there is an edge or reference pointing to it if there is no edge it removes it kills it
is this clear now even you are one of the interviews core problem like number of distinct
eye lines is actually like garbage collector algorithm itself how that works this is something
that I'm talking about you can actually see how this garbage collector is built and how
heap error is being cleaned when there is no reference pointer pointing to it anything so
guys I hope you understood like actually what is pass-by value versus pass-by reference give
me thumbs up guys once if you are able to understand them clear right now let's go and
explore one thing now I we say that now the problem statement let's say I build a simple
objects let's say person one let me copy this one simple object this is a person one I created
nothing else let's say I have percent two if I do this it is you know copying the reference
still right it is copying the reference this is what we have learned right now but I want
this data to be cloned this data to be cloned such a way that in in heap area I create a new
object taking this out values is my point here guys when I say clone what I meant by that
you can say copy that's I want to create a copy now I don't want to talk about deep versus
shallow copy first but I'm first do you need a break guys or should I continue it's one hour
24 minutes do you need a break I can come back and talk on this topic okay let's take break
five minute works right five minutes is fine we'll take five minutes and come back
let's start we'll come back and discuss
guys is everyone back okay great now if you're back let me state the problem statement clearly
for you guys to understand this one right now what was happening earlier when we are
passing by reference let's say there was an object one let me do one thing let me copy that
part I don't want to write it again let's say okay we had this two objects now this
we were the next line what we were doing next line was we were actually doing second image
second name object equal to first name when we were doing this we know that just the second
name pointer or the reference value is updated with this one right but we don't want that thing
to happen in our heap in our heap what we want to do is even when this line is done we want
something like let's say there is a name one equal to first which will this will point and
then there is a name again a first and the other will one point okay and then there will be also
name second which will be relying there is this clear what I'm trying to say is that when I'm
trying to do says this one instead of pass by value can you convert this pass by reference
into pass by value convert pass by reference into pass by value is this clear like how can
we do this now this is for doing this thing there are two methods one is called shallow copy
one is called deep copy the methods that we are going to learn now are the way the way
we can do it this both are not perfect solutions okay not perfect solutions in order to do a deep
deep copy when we say deep deep copy I'll come to that point in JS we had one library called
Lodash Lodash dot copy function used to do that now what that used to do what we are going to
do I'll come to that point but is this problem statement clear what we are going to do is that
we will be converting and like pass by reference into pass by value and we'll be learning two ways
of doing it one is shallow copy and deep copy and then I'll talk about something like a Lodash
library is this clear guys let's let's explore this one how we can do this now now if you see
it here I have one person object called which is having name agent address now when I'm doing it
this way person 2 equal to person 1 is it a pass by value or pass by reference firstly reference
right how many of you agree it is a reference guys okay I see all people agreeing with the
reference great now if you want to convert this into pass by value if you want to clone a copy
or create a new copy how can we do it any ideas we have seen this we have seen this earlier but
just think of it like how we can do it if I want to if I want to do it pass by value I have to
pick individual individual elements right because these are primitives inside our object data type
isn't it do you agree if I can pick a name and create a name this will be a yeah so Kiran
power suggests us this one right what she says is that what he says is that let's say person
2 dot name equal to person 1 dot name right then we have something like person 2 dot age
equal to person 1 dot H this is what up in the immediate answer is something that we get to
mind or mind right the what is the easier way of doing this what is the easier way of doing this
can I do it this way that I use parade operator that pull each and every field out of it and
create a new object using this way instead of directly assigning a pointer how many of
you are able to understand this point I see only one thumbs up guys all other people are
able to relate this one like how I'm trying to copy is that I'm converting and when I'm
spreading it it will spread one by one element right one by one element inside this object
instead we are not getting a reference we are actually getting the values one by one okay but
do you see any problem here still let me let me try to do one thing let me show you that this
won't create a problem first what I'll do person 1 dot name I'll update as let's say Kiran okay
now if I console log person 1 and console log person 2 I'll show that firstly this deep this
copy is working okay let me remove all other console logs for a second
if you see here one is I'm getting Adam the other one is getting Kiran so do you see this
I'm changing one value but the other one is not getting change this means that we are actually
converted a password value into pass by reference I mean pass by reference into pass by value do
you guys agree with this point like are you able to understand what we have done it so is there
anyone who don't understand this point what what just happened okay now the next thing let's say
if I if I do something like let's say person 1 dot address dot city which I update with
Hyderabad now once I do this I re-execute this one now do you see one mistake guys still the
is changing for both of them when I'm updating it are you able to relate this one that it is
not copying completely it is not converting completely from pass by reference to pass by
value do you understand reason behind it because in whenever in heap right whenever in heap this
address object is also created by reference like this will be pulled as a separate object
this is object inside object this address here in person was also storing a reference
right whenever I'm extracting it when I'm extracting it actually here also when I'm
extracting address I'm also getting a reference but I'm not getting this object converted into
primitives this is what we call it as a shallow copy is this clear wherever you are it you are
copying the elements converting from pass by reference into pass by value at one level of
items you're converting it one level of items clear guys no guys anyone who didn't understand
my point this point I just want to know I see only one reaction just want to know that how
many of you understand what shallow copy is I say three okay four now how do you think we
can address this issue just thinking think it curiously guys this is also we have seen an
example of this one think of it this one like how can you actually completely convert into a
primitive like just the logic behind whenever someone says then to create a copy it is that
they're creating a copy by converting a reference they're breaking the reference creating a new
object and put adding a new reference separately so it's like pass by converting from pass by
reference to pass by value so just think of it if something clicking you okay just let me know
how many of you understand this thing when I write JSON dot stringify I do this how many
of you understand what is just happening here what does this line do okay let me show you this one
let me show you this one I execute it again now do you see this this object is converted
into string both key and value key value pairs are converted into string do you see this when
I do JSON dot stringify it is converted into string and what is a string what is a data type
of string is it a primitive or non-primitive it's primitive right again if I'm able to convert this
primitive of string into an object our problem is solved isn't it so let's do this thing let's
say I create an object person 3 JSON dot pass which again converts a string into an object
JSON dot stringify person one okay now once I do this let's say I again I'll update this
things I'll again copy and paste this one so that I can show you that person one nine three
I love I'll comment everything on there okay now let's see this if this is working fine
do you see this when we updated person once address our city as hydrobot it worked fine
but here it is mum by itself so this is what a deep copies you understand this point like
how this is converted so do you understand the power that what JSON stringify and pass
whenever we are doing this hope you understand what is actually behind the scenes happening okay
firstly we are converting a whole object into string then we are converting back into an object
format which is converting like like reference our reference data type into a string then into
again a reference data type creating a whole copy this is what a deep copy looks like deep
clone or deep copy this is point here guys what is shallow copy deep copy versus pass by value
pass by reference all these points are clear is there anyone who is having doubts if there is
anyone still having any doubts let me know I'll re-explain this one I've explained pretty much
simply I also talked about what happens behind the scenes or what type of data type we are
converting into other one okay I hope no one forgets this one this are a pretty simple examples
and this is applicable for any of the you know language and why do I say that a deep
copy is also not a complete copy the reason I'll tell you is that what if there is a function
let's say I say get email function
let's say this is a function that added okay why this deep copy also not completely works I'll
talk about this when we convert this function let's say if I do this person stringify now
if you see when I'm converting into stringify do you see anywhere function
no right so json stringify and pass works for the objects pure objects but not which
it contains functions or any other you know it works let's say if I pick it up array also
let's say I have an array I create one two three four five I have an array let me clear
this console and again reprint it now if you see for array it is still converting into string
but do you see it not working for the function this is the reason why I say that even the
deep copy is not a complete copy do you agree with my point whatever deep copy we just learned
it is not a complete copy the solution for this one actually you know was built by was built
by library called Lodash is a using only way to make the copies in json that's a one of the
the other way or what is actually used in the project level right I'm talking about that one
if you see this method cloned it Lodash cloned it you can explore actually the this is a built
in library which will give you you know cloning an object if if cloning an object would happen
that easy like you can do json spring if I pass we wouldn't need any library and if you see there's
a weekly downloads of 11 lakhs the spread operator copy the functions it does you know copy the
functions we name but again the function isn't stored in the heap area right it is like it is
a separate execution context if you go from that point of view it will also have a reference
pointer functions also are stored somewhere right in the memory in the global space so those will
also get we'll get an reference point so even if you copy if you are updating that function
everything will be updated so that's an problem so this is the library guys that helps us in
order to clone it you can explore like document we can see the documentation if you see what it
does like if you want to clone an object again you just do underscore which is a Lodash import
dot cloned deep you pass an object you'll get it and whenever you try to compare it here whenever
you're trying to compare 0th index you're not able to like match it because those not reference
pointers are not same so that's the reason why we get and false because these are array of objects
it's really difficult to clone this type of things like how would you clone combinations
of combinations of combinations so this particular library is actually handling those use cases is
this clear guys so I hope someone asked you to clone it someone asked you to do it an interview
will be able to explain this like hey we can do using JSON Stringify and pass and even spread
operator but this works up to an extent when it try to you know further complicated you can say
that I'll use Lodash library which will help me to because there is a famous saying in the software
engineering is don't reinvent the wheel until it is unavoidable okay so when there is a solution
available try to go and use it and if that solution is creating a problem like it is a
not a memory intensive or time operation intensive then go and create your own library is this clear
guys so just want to recheck with you guys like are you able to understand call bind apply and
let's say I'll repeat all the topics in the iPad itself so that I just want to check with you if
you are able to understand all these points so call bind apply pass by value pass by reference
shallow copy deep copy this using spread operator this using JSON parts dot JSON Stringify
object so guys are this can we do an example of Lodash I have to import I'll show that in
future Kiran okay I'll show that in future when projects will take that leverage will like when
we build it so guys how many of you are able to clear with this points if can you give me
thumbs up if you need me to revise I can revise in our five minutes if you want me to revise let
me know other seconds again when we go to the next class I'll revise this concepts and then
we'll move forward okay so is there anyone who don't understand this concepts let me know like
I'll go I'll start the doubt session but we'll do one of the polyfill example it's not part of
curriculum it is like out of my own interest I am trying to you know build it okay polyfill
for call what's the time complexity Vinay good question let me see this
so it says we go often since it's going through all the elements right objects it is going
one by one element then converting into string format right the level of complexity let's say
yeah if you have like object inside an object inside an object inside an object then it will
become like going again for one level it will go into n so it can go to n power n also depending
upon the level of complexity you have but it goes one by one and convert into string then
parses also again converting into so if you are doing first n operations then you are doing
again an operation so it is n square operations okay guys I hope the concepts are clear if the
concepts are clear can we start with the doubt session so that I'll pick it up a polyfill and
we'll explore what is polyfill and everything okay I'll start it and hang around guys hang in
so that will you also get to learn few things more okay what happens right there are some
interviewers right there are there's some crazy interviews what they do is that they ask you to
implement library functions they ask you like hey you know how can you write you know use the
call bind apply everything is working fine but what if there is an use case comes to you that
hey can you implement call or what if there is an use case when you want to build your own custom
logic like if I say for the deep copy low-clone dip was there now if I ask you to you know build
algorithm which will be actually cloning in a deep it wouldn't take more than one day or two days
for you to write it down because they're giving in a part of library or multiple utility methods
that you are using the reusable right now that same problem we have to solve for the call function
now let's say taking back going back picking up the same example what we had for call now let's
say I have this function I'll copy here to refresh our brain and then approaching this
problem okay this is what what call was doing call was changing the context of this and
executing the function isn't it that is what we have understood and that is what we have learned
right guys now if someone comes and tell you that hey write down your I don't want to give
you a call function write down your own custom function and execute it how would you do it just
try to give me a top-level idea then I'll give you the brief idea how it is done guys
what would be the first step how would you get a like like you know the function available on
get email function how would you make all function available on this firstly let's say you want to
he'll ask you to create a my call function which will do the same work as call
how can you make my call available to all the functions in the JS like you remember
in array you have length index of in object you have has more on properties how those were
available add new function to get email proto right killer you are on the right part but do
I have to add it on get email function only or what if I can add it to whole function type only
data type it would be great right every function whatever create you will have your own custom
function every right so let's say I'll give you this function dot prototype dot my call
let's say you design this function let's say it's a function and this function what it is
generally taking ice it is taking two things this context whichever new context you want to
update with and a list of arguments let's say which are coming comma separated right
this was a function syntax isn't it now let's think of it how would you change it how would
you change it how would you change this context now let's say I can say first and first line itself
I'll say that a current context can you update this current context from this context okay I'll
say that update the current context as this context okay once I get this I'll create a
new key value pair I'll create a new key value pair and I'll call that new key as let's say
const instead of const let's say I have a you know new I'll say prop math dot random now how
many of you understand what math dot random does it gives a value from 0 to 1 right it gives you
a random value so a certain range whenever you want it right now I'll write one condition guys
I just want you to understand what this line is and I'll explain on this but I wanted to focus on
this now what do you understand by this point what I'm saying is that I'm creating a new key
I'm checking if that prop is already existing in this context if that is existing right then
create me a new random value until unless I get a unique prop I'm repeating again whatever context
user is passing since they are passing an object inside that it will have a key value pairs I am
checking whether the new key that I created using math dot random if that is already existing in
object I have to create a new key so I'm trying to create a new key until unless I'm getting a
unique key is this clear point right this is what I'm doing once I get a new key what I'll do here
I'll say that hey current context inside that take me the prop and assign this now the what
this is pointing to here I'll show you while debugging actually this is pointing to the function
itself and which function like you call gmail.call right this function comes into the this okay now
once I have this what I'll do is that in order to get result that's how you get a result how
I'll call this like current.prop I'll get pass on list of arguments and execute it then I
will delete the current.prop and return the result guys how many of you are able to understand this
one if you're not able to understand that's okay because it takes time to get it but let them just
trying to see if you are able to follow up I see two people great no worries great let me do this
I'll copy this function call and and I'll make it as such that you know my call okay now let
me put a debugger here and show you guys how this works
okay
okay okay I didn't declare this array let me get this an array
now again I failed to load it school okay I have to call this function as school
city sport
no so coming back to this point guys this is clear right and this what we are passing
this context whatever object we have to change and then list of arguments whatever we are actually
passing if you see here we'll be able to see inside the arcs we have three things let me
minimize this call stack I don't need a break points one I don't need a call stack but I need
this one this is screen what poly fields yeah Archana it is poly fields are like building
whatever library is there now the call bind apply these are built-in libraries for us since
what JavaScript has been developed what if there's a use case in interviewer ask like can you build
the library itself okay those are itself called a polyfill so I'm saying that polyfill for the
call writing your custom logic if you can build that call function like whatever call was doing
can we do it that with our own logic with our own algorithm okay so guys till here any doubts
like in this we are passing this where we are having the first name last name and age and
we are passing this three parameters guys give me thumbs up thumbs down I have more than 20
people in class till here no doubts right now let's let's see let's see what's happening if I
go click play if you see in the current context the current context got updated with whatever
this context we passed okay so we are having these three things now inside this I'm getting
something called as prop now here if you see inside this inside this current context a prop
is created with the value as this one I mean inside this function a new key value a new
property is created called prop which is having from 0 to 1 value and 0.7 and the reason this
while loop didn't get executed is because inside this object current context there is no key like
0.7 this is clear till here is this clear line number 23 what just happened guys please react
if this things are clear till here okay now here let's see what is actually happening in this now
what I just say that hey I'll take this prop I'll use it as a key and you know when I'm
checking for the this operator what is pointing where this is pointing to now if you see get
email function dot my call now whenever you are calling email function email function is actually
calling my call in by default inside my call function this will point to get email function
isn't it that is what we are getting here this is clear so what I'm doing it inside this object
I'm taking this this as a key and value as a this email function now if I go and click a play here
if you see inside the current context I'm having key of 0.736 and value as a function and I'm
having this objects object values Adam Smith and age 25 now when I go and execute it now what
happens when I go and execute it now remember how I'm executing it now whenever I do let's say if
you see this what is what just happened here let's say I create a const current context if you see
here if I copy this let's say these are three values we are having also I'm having something
like 0.736 and it is having this get email function overall right now whenever I try to
do this execute this current context start execute 0.736 and I try to call it now whenever I'm
calling it this way always inside this function this operator will refer to this keys isn't it
this is what we have learned in earlier class when we are learning this now that is what I leverage
here I've said that hey I'm calling that function inside the object and I'm passing whatever expected
arguments like schools it is ports it is expecting so I'm passing all those arguments from the arcs
if you see in the arcs I'm having these three values okay now once I do that let's say if I
go back now if you see what I do here I have in the result I click play let me remove this logic
just a second okay now click this now let me comment above line so that I can show you this
is working as expected actually it doesn't need to return also it doesn't need to return also
executing this thing itself will solve our problem right let's say I write down our console log
executing from polyfill okay now if I clear this and execute it let me click play and play
now do you see this executing from polyfill and then we were able to print Adam Steady Smith
because this is how we can build my call function so guys I hope you understood this one how this
is working and I hope you liked it this is something an extra content yeah we are deleting that
context again we don't need it right so that's how Kiran it should be done because if you go
for interview purposes so I'm actually planning to do one thing is that maintain a separate
repository where I can build you know poly fills and store it also machine coding problems and
its solutions maybe a website one thing I can do is that I can build it I'll initial layout I'll
do it then I'll create issues if someone can if we want to contribute I'll create the issues and
they can contribute it okay so that it will be used for you also and you will have like
something open source contribution so what do you guys think should we do that where you write down
poly fills for the most of the JS functions also machine coding problems like I'll create issues
and it will take some time for me to build that layout and do it I'll do it and then I'll give it
to you so that for you right react practice will be also happening parallelly also you will be
practicing that thing very HTML CSS also you'll have an like practice like where you raise a PR
you go through the code review then everything right so it will be a great exercise according
to me but anyone who is willing to interested who they can contribute in repo if not they can
like leave it and if we get luckily more stars and if your contribution is great you can add
that in resume that I have done a contribution in open source okay so no guys if that is the
this point is clear I would like to end my session today here itself I hope you got to learn few
good topics today this is how we'll be continuously building upon knowledge on the JS part and then
we'll move towards you know closure of JS and from next class on right interesting topics
interesting interesting topics already I talked about single thread I talked about introduced
event loop on top level but we'll see all of them behind the scenes on how they are working
we'll talk about more async JS in three sessions where I'll go completely in depth of asynchronous
JavaScript how actually JavaScript is magically handling many things and why it is so powerful
right how things have been happening so we'll explore this one and without having any like
locking mechanism if you go for any object oriented programming languages right where
you have multi-threading concept you have locks on each part of code you need to have a lock
because two threads cannot simultaneously work on one part of code so without even having those
use cases JS works clearly so we'll explore that part but I'll take the doubts now guys so
whoever don't have doubts they can feel free to drop but if someone is having doubts hang
around I'll take them so Kabir can you share your Kanban link I'll check that
firstly we'll check that and then we'll come to other contest outs
so I have this I create task hyphen one okay you have the create button cool now I have
let's say another task okay I have this that's fine task hyphen two create cool you know
this is fine this is fine if I double-click it's working fine now
Kabir if I click once it is loading okay in responsive layout let me
this is away this is this level to this extent or let's say any extent right
okay there you don't have filter itself I okay you converted into this way okay
now let's say I have this I click this one and you have only one item if I click this one you
have only one item if I double-click it okay it is not being created if I double-click it
okay interesting
let me go through the source code
firstly when I'm clicking double-click okay one thing when you go for responsive
right in mobile it is working but here how do you do a double-click is a bit different I guess
because double-click operation itself that event listener itself is not listening right
let's say double-click it's not working
there are some issues people have faced yet they want to go with jQuery we don't need jQuery
in mobile it is working because it is rendering that way it works fine but when it comes to
the type of event being flagged right when I'm clicking here let's say when I'm double-clicking
also it is printing something okay but where this is being printing over is being print from
this part let's say if I double-click it always it is listening to a single click it is not
listening to a double-click in a mobile view whereas if you expand it a bit further it won't
work here also if I remove this pane I mean do you see a difference in the cursor Kabir
like whenever I'm hovering over it right it is giving me a round symbol whenever I'm expanding
it it is actually when I remove this right it becomes a pointer from even point of view I have
to check on this like why double-click is not working what is a substitute like while you are
testing it it is not a problem with your code it is a problem with how this Chrome browser is
rendering let's say if I go with some other browser I don't have like other than Safari
I don't use Safari much it's a problem with browser how they are rendering not with your
working in mobile right oh I don't need to make this as a primary okay here I don't even view it
this is not that developer friendly actually when it comes to Safari Safari doesn't really
help us to you know do it I mean it won't give you let you do the responsive but do one thing
Kabir try to see in your system if you have any other browser right I don't seem to have many
other browsers in my machine let me recheck if I have any browser other than Chrome and Safari
you can see in Mozilla Firefox if you have it in your machine once install Mozilla Firefox because
it is not a problem from your code because code is working fine even in the mobile and this one
it is just that browser how they render it okay how they're listening to the clicks actually
okay so other than that thing things are fine and the other doubts that you had related to
contest if you have question ready it's okay fine let me know if you have the question available
I shall give it share it then we'll pick it up okay great let me copy this logic
commented is the option can always let me go back to the code base
let me do one thing I'll push this code once
so have you guys gone through Git class did you get to explore that one the links that we have
shared I mean did you guys get the chance to not yet we'll do this work okay explore that guys too
okay so I have this button click me document dot get element add event listener click function
I've added on the my div okay cool and console log div clicked then you have document of
great element by ID my button which are listening to the button specifically click me and you have
an event you have stopped the propagation now by default it is a bubbling right by default it is a
bubbling now when I click whenever I use a clicks button it will stop bubbling out
that's cool doesn't matter anyways it will now only the button click will be locked to
the console when the button is clicked and button click will be locked to the console button
this is half the code is it okay both are there are clicked and button clicked because
they haven't printed anything in the div click right there is nothing in the my div clicked
to print anything okay so firstly there is no chance let's go by the process of elimination
Kabir do you by any chance do you think this fourth option will be correct by any chance
when you're clicking the outer div when I click the outer div the div will be locked to the
console that they've clicked is locked to the console this is true or false like firstly do
you see anywhere div clicked present in the content if you see here I'm having this container
no no it is there here no it is printed here whenever user clicks on at this part div it
will be printing div clicked okay now the div in case right firstly only when div is
clicked top level div is clicked shortly it should console log div clicked isn't it this
point should exist now let me show you by creating index.html itself okay
but you will be only able to verify this one whenever user clicks our dev right it's a CSS
should be there without that you won't be able to verify where that container button clicked
first option option or okay what Archana says yes sir this went wrong or I also selected button
click first option right but option fourth they say but the correct option is a first option
huh okay now if you see the by the context right let's say if I go by I add the script here
firstly do that do you have any border and spacing and padding given so that you'll get
to know that firstly nothing is mentioned so you don't know where the div exists and button
exists whatever you are clicking is you are able to click only the button first
so I did anyone catch this point I mean if you see in the question Archana and even when
render this if I render this let's say if I render this live server so I won't say that you guys
are wrong but from the question point of you right do you see div anywhere that div wrapper
only if you click it let's say only if you click it here div clicked will be printed but
something that you are seeing only is button right Kabir let's let's validate all of them
let's validate all of them four points whatever you guys had see most of the times right it's
good that you guys are picking it up and coming to back to me I appreciate that effort because
there might be a certain confusion but let's understand this this this can happen to anyone
even if I put a quiz competition quiz sort of thing here it can happen but now let's say only
button will click will be locked to the console when the button is clicked if I click it now do
you see this button click is being locked firstly option one is right because by default we are
going with the event bubbling concept when until unless you flag it a flag whether it's a bubbling
out or capturing face and we made a propagation stop right if you if you let's say if you didn't
if you didn't do this even stop propagation and since event listener is available for this one
not here but here you will be able to see for both of them let's say if I click it button click and
they click both will be coming okay since its event stop is there by default on interface you
are able to see only button so first sentence is clear now what happens with the MCQ suggestion
is like whenever you see that first statement is right right you should go with it until unless
there are multiple answers okay now now second thing if you say button clicked will be locked
to the console when button is clicked if you see this is also right only right if I clicked
it only button click will option 2 is also right isn't it option 3 is definitely wrong
option 3 is definitely wrong and div click will be locked to console when div is clicked surely
this is also a right only but you have to be able to see that div being clicked if you see
I'm clicking div only div is getting incremented so you have actually three right answers according
to an UI developer friend and developer only one wrong answer which is this one the question
should have been actually so one rule for the MCQ's right what is a definite rule for MCQ's
right I agree that you lost the point lost the marks it's not your mistake I'll ask the team
to work on it okay I'll share that this question to them but remember one MCQ how that MCQ works
is you have to check first option if it is true go with that if the second one is also right right
mainly whenever a paper setter does got it Archana I'll try to highlight this guys that
you lost you know marks because of this one but actually question should have been reverse
isn't it like both a divine clicked will be locked to the console when button is clicked
like which wouldn't be the right answer in the poor of those options because three options are
the fourth one is wrong it should have been fourth one right so I'll check with the team
to fix this up but by whenever you go for MCQ's right here or anywhere validate from the top
ABCD go over if you feel is right go for that one mostly because that is how they will defend
themselves like if I'm defending now myself that hey first option I gave that is right it should
go right if you go for any competitive exams that's how paper setter will look into it he
might not give the other one if you select other one then there might be you cannot challenge them
okay but from your point of view guys this question that whatever you have attempted I
agree with your answer also that is also right but it's just that I think I have to change can
you give me the question number Kabir this is first question itself is it
option options were toggled okay give me the question number I'll ask them to update this
update this one as such that I have this copied also in the content I'll copy this content such
that last time to update the question as like which one might not be the right I
just need MCQ 14 okay great I'll ask them to update it pardon me guys like one thing
right I can tell this right I'll ask them like if we can if we can address this one okay the
second question this is something okay dev my dev okay get element by ID adding a new class
call highlight and we're trying to do console dot div dot class name okay
we are adding no class name should have highlight space box
this highlight okay we are adding it to the last so it should be a box and highlight will
be locked to the console in the code is that possible to get by ID and add a class name
huh you can do that now let me show you this one that we can do this anytime this is right
okay this is the part okay now once I let's say I write down div to just to see on the screen
I have Dave if you see box highlight is something rendering you can use query
selectors or get by ID get by class name anything you can use like you in instead of
get element by ID if I get by class name now class name of let's say box this should also
work so sure if I show you just let me check this
okay having two things see the error no just a thing I am getting the two things here do
okay I have only one item elements I'm getting elements guys autocorrect okay I'll type it
down fastly now whatever suggestion I've got I've clicked that one but let me see if this is okay
get element by class name but still I'm getting an error document it's not a function
even when I do get elements by class name it should give me in a box if I have multiple
classes also that doesn't should should not be having an issue okay I see where this is
coming from so what what's happening here is that so you move to diff you are getting two
diffs here my div and 0th div in the browser if I go inside the body okay I'm having only
my diff then when I getting by class why I'm getting two values that's what I'm thinking
but for IDs right Kabir for IDs for IDs like IDs will be unique right so you will be always
receiving only one value for class name I'm thinking like why I'm getting two values here
firstly like where this is actually getting created let's say if I if I have multiple things
other let's say if I have another diff my div one and I try to save this I go back
let's me render this one again okay now what is an issue that you are able to identify for each
ID they are creating a duplicate if I don't have an ID let's say if I don't have an ID it will fix
it I am assuming that if I don't have an ID it will address the issue let's say remove this an ID
okay still I don't have an ID but now okay whenever first and foremost thing is like
the basic concept is whenever I'm getting by class name I have I can have multiple values so
whatever div element I'm having it will be an array of elements because it's in
plural form I cannot do class list directly that's where I'm committing mistake so one
thing always you can do play around is like you if you have this derivative element odd
0th element then this will be working fine that's my understanding but let me see
this is working fine as of now because class name if you see this is getting updated but
ID Kabir hope you got it that get element by ID gives you the unique value all the time and it
can be only one thing when you're getting my class name there can be multiple elements so
there they might be accessing those through this syntax is this clear
yeah yeah it will work on so in order to avoid confusion right go with query selector query
selector all most of the times but if you see anywhere get element by ID ID will always give
unique class name is for common group of people and when you get common group it is always an
array of elements that's the reason why if you see when I coded actual machine coding and everything
I've selected query selector in order to avoid confusion I go with query selector
okay anything else guys
so if there are no other doubts we'll close the session Kabir we have stretched lot
okay then why we use get element by id if you have a see get element by id comes into the
use case when you have unique value in order to identify diffs if dom right if you want to access
let's say let's think in from the coding problem point of view if you if I give you a unique
identifier like let's say it's an array you have an index out of it right you can get value out
of index directly by easily but when you that's how that's how that method works get element by
id is like everything is stored in a key value pairs like each id is acting as a key values acting
as a whole div element that's how that property works document dot get element by id get element
by class name is where you're having a one class name multiple diffs are stored in a hash map
I mean like I can talk about data structure but how they are stored it will take time
they'll ask you to I mean
uh it's good to get proficient many people want to trick it around right
they try to confuse you but you should know there are three types of
two selectors and the common things are query selectors
okay okay I hope I solved out guys so we close the session today I'll end the session today here
stretch much thank you kabir thank you for asking them and no no worries no worries kabir so I hope
you tested once in mozilla firebox once okay because it's not a problem of your code it's
in responsive design it is a double click event which is not able to listen okay
or check for the remedy if you find remedy also let me know like how you can handle double shift
double click you can explore one technology called web view
web view I'm giving you this context try to explore web view okay once how that web view works
so hello guys that's good night take care see you see you in the next class bye guys
I'm stopping screen share bye guys
you